{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "An event involving these two countries is the subject of a Quentin Tarantino-produced documentary, Freedom’s Fury. During that event, one participant saw “about 4,000 stars” after being struck by Valentin Prokopov. Ervin Zador’s face wound nearly led to a riot in Melbourne during a 1956 Olympic water polo match between, for ten points, what two countries, one of which had just had a revolution crushed in Budapest by the other?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union and Hungary",
        "in either order",
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in place of Soviet Union"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was briefly restored to power by Zhang Xun. This man benefited from the Articles of Favourable Treatment, though that was revised following a coup by Feng Yuxiang. Prince Zaifeng ruled as a regent for this man, who was tutored in his early years by Reginald Johnston. This man, who was forced to abdicate at age 6, was the subject of a Bernardo Bertolucci biopic that detailed his path from Cixi’s successor to puppet leader of Manchukuo. For ten points, name this final emperor of China.",
      "answer": [
        "Puyi",
        "Xuantong Emperor"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, the ambassador Mikelis was shot trying to board the Guerrier, prompting the Asia to open fire. Prime Minister Wellington sacked this battle’s winning commander, who had controversially provoked a showdown by anchoring his fleet across from the losing side’s horseshoe formation once reinforcements from Henri de Rigny and Lodewijk [lode-veek] Heyden arrived. This battle, which was prompted by the losing side’s decision to reject the Treaty of London, featured an allied fleet under Edward Codrington defeating the Ottoman navy. For ten points, name this decisive 1827 battle of the Greek War of Independence.",
      "answer": "Battle of Navarino"
    },
    {
      "question": "This collection was published with an acrostic explanation of its history that spells out the word “ricercar.” This collection’s second piece is a six-voice fugue that was one of the first-ever compositions for piano; that selection from this work answered a challenge made at the Sanssouci Palace in Potsdam by a Prussian king who wrote the original theme. For ten points, name this collection of keyboard music by Johann Sebastian Bach based on a theme given to him by Frederick the Great.",
      "answer": [
        "The Musical Offering or Das Musikalisches Opfer",
        "BWV 1079"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s story was popularized in a ballad created by his friend Wallace Saunders. A sound that mimicked a whippoorwill call became identified with this man, who built a six-tube whistle for his work with the Illinois Central. This man told Sim Webb, a fireman, to leap out of their car, saving his life in an accident that killed only this man. For ten points, name this engineer who became a folk hero after heroically slowing his train prior to a collision in 1900.",
      "answer": "Casey Jones"
    },
    {
      "question": "Though his mother offered his weight in gold as compensation for his corpse, this man was buried by William Malet. This man’s brother divided his land between this man and Beorn. After a shipwreck, this man was captured and taken to Beaurain by Guy, Count of Ponthieu. This brother of Sweyn won a battle that followed Fulford, and at his most famous battle, this man fought alongside Leofwine. An arrow to the eye legendarily killed, for ten points, what Anglo-Saxon king who was defeated by William the Conqueror at Hastings?",
      "answer": [
        "Harold Godwinson",
        "Harold II"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "TheOfficial Bulletin wasthedailynewspaperofthisorganization,whichreleasedfilmslikePersching’s Answer. A piece created by this organization shows a gorilla holding a struggling woman and contains the caption “Destroy this Mad Brute.” Workers in this organization gave over 7.5 million speeches during the changing of film reels; those speakers were known as Four Minute Men. Posters encouraging civilians to buy liberty bonds were created by, for ten points, what committee that used propaganda to build support for American participation in World War I?",
      "answer": [
        "Creel Committee",
        "Committee On Public Information"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Publius Mucius Scaevola was the last holder of this position to have written for the Annales Maximi, a yearly set of annals published by its holders. While serving as king, Numa Pompilius created this position, whose final holder was a member of the Second Triumvirate alongside Octavian and Marc Antony. Lepidus once held this position, which served a role similar to the rex sacrorum. The title of “Greatest bridge builder” was bestowed on, for ten points, what office that oversaw the priesthood of Roman religion?",
      "answer": [
        "Pontifex Maximus",
        "Greatest Bridge Builder before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Elizabeth Lee Hazen and Rachel Fuller Brown named the first antifungal antibiotic in honor of this state. George Soper failed to collect samples from a woman in this state, where Dr. Sarah Josephine Baker’s efforts led to the hospitalization and quarantine of Mary Mallon, who carried the pathogen responsible for typhoid fever. For ten points, name this state where public health officials wrote symbols in chalk on people during six-second medical examinations administered to immigrants at Ellis Island.",
      "answer": "New York"
    },
    {
      "question": "The evacuation of Walnut Hills was overseen by Andrew Ellicott after the signing of this treaty. The cessation of a line between the Pearl and Perdido Rivers was agreed upon as part of this treaty. Ownership rights over the Tombigbee and Natchez districts were discussed as part of this treaty, which resolved the West Florida Controversy and gave the United States navigation rights of the Mississippi River. A prominent Federalist negotiated, for ten points, what 1795 treaty between the U.S. and Spain?",
      "answer": [
        "Pinckney’s Treaty",
        "Treaty of San Lorenzo",
        "Treaty of Madrid",
        "Treaty of Friendship, Limits, and Navigation Between Spain and the United States"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man captured the cloth industry of Lille after a decisive victory at Mons-en-Pevele. This man carried out a burning at the stake on an island in the Seine to curb the influence of the Knights Templar, though his conquest of Flanders was set back at the Battle of the Golden Spurs. The Babylonian Captivity began when this man feuded with Pope Boniface VIII, forcing the papacy to move to Avignon. For ten points, name this French monarch who was named for his good looks.",
        "answer": [
          "Philip IV",
          "Philip the Fair"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Philip IV ordered the execution of this last Grand Master of the Knights Templar in 1314. The Freemasonry movement traces its connection to the Knights Templar to a secret act by this man.",
        "answer": "Jacques de Molay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this region in 1965, the Long Shot underground nuclear weapons test was carried out on Amchitka. In1946,anearthquakeinthisregiondestroyedUnimak’sScotchCapLighthouse,whichpreventedtsunami warnings from being relayed; that disaster inspired the creation of the Pacific Tsunami Warning Center. In June 1942, the Japanese invaded this region’s islands of Kiska and Attu. The Bering Sea and Pacific Ocean are divided by, for ten points, what chain of islands that extends southwest from the largest US state?",
        "answer": "Aleutian Islands"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Aleutian Islands campaign, the Americans recovered one of these objects on Akutan after the death of Tadayoshi Koga. In 1941, Shigenori Nishikaichi destroyed one of these objects on Niihau to prevent the Americans from getting it.",
        "answer": [
          "a functional Mitsubishi A6M Zero aircraft",
          "either",
          "both names"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one work by this philosopher, the drunken Alcibiades bursts in after various luminaries take turns giving speeches about love. This thinker postulated the existence of abstract forms, such as the Good. Another work by this founder of the Academy envisions an ideal city-state and includes the Allegory of the Cave. For ten points, name this author of the Symposium and the Republic, a Greek philosopher who wrote many dialogues featuring his teacher Socrates.",
        "answer": "Plato"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Platonic dialogue is the origin of the problem of whether “the pious” is loved by the gods becauseitisgood,orifitisgoodbecauseitislovedbythegods;thatisthiswork’seponymous“dilemma.”",
        "answer": "Euthyphro , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This piece of legislation is depicted as a stone tripping a carriage in which the driver asks his companion “Do slack up a little there, Horace.” The Congressional Library holds the original draft of this document, written by Jacob Brinkerhoff. The namesake of this bill was a member of the Free Soil Party. This bill passed in the House, but was stopped by the Southern-dominated Senate, causing it to never actually be added to the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. For ten points, name this bill that would have outlawed slavery in territories gained in the Mexican-American War.",
        "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Even if the Wilmot Proviso had passed the Senate, it may not have gotten into the final treaty anyway; after all, this American diplomat ignored his instructions from President Polk and negotiated the treaty on his own.",
        "answer": "Nicholas Trist"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this war, the central government outlined a campaign based on the Marshall Plan that called for the “3 Rs” of reconstruction, rehabilitation, and reconciliation. A successful invasion of the port of Calabar occurred during this war’s Operation Tiger Claw. The largest civilian airlift in history was carried out during this war, in which Joseph Achuzie failed to repel an invasion at Port Harcourt. Muhammadu Buhari commanded a battalion during, for ten points, what 1967-70 war over a secessionist Igbo state in Nigeria?",
        "answer": "Biafran War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Early in his career, this man commanded a division during the Biafran War. After this man escaped death in a failed 1976 coup, he led as the head of a military government for three years; he was then democratically elected president in 1999 and 2003.",
        "answer": "Olusegun Obasanjo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The subject of this poem is “loosed from its dream of life” “six miles from earth.” The author of this poem later noted that its subject would have been a “short small man” who “looked like the fetus in the womb,” “hunched upside-down in his little sphere.” This five line poem about the helplessness of war jarringly ends “When I died they washed me out [...] with a hose.” For ten points, name this World War II poem whose subject operated machine guns under a B-24 bomber until his death.",
        "answer": "The Death of the Ball Turret Gunner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This American poet and tower operator in the Air Force wrote “The Death of the Ball Turret Gunner.”",
        "answer": "Randall Jarrell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the wake of this event, Denis Berezovsky served one day as head of his country’s navy, then defected. Ilya Ponomarev was exiled shortly after he became the only representative of his country’s lower house to vote against this action, which critics claimed was a violation of the Budapest Memorandum. The Federal Assembly ratified a Treaty of Accession that officially approved this action, which followed the Euromaidan protest movement. “Little Green Men” helped carry out this action. The War in Donbass largely resulted from, for ten points, what action in which Vladimir Putin invaded an eastern European peninsula in 2014?",
        "answer": "Russian annexation of the Crimea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the various international laws that deemed Russia’s annexation illegal was this set of accords, signed in Belarus in 1991, that established the CIS and declared the USSR no longer existant.",
        "answer": "Belavezha Accords"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jesse Langdon was the final surviving member of this group, which frequently met in the Menger Bar. This group, which was sometimes described as its founder’s “Weary Walkers,” had a 50th anniversary stamp that commemorated the death of its captain “Bucky” O’Neill, who had died at Kettle Hill. Alongside the Buffalo Soldiers, this group fought against the forces of Antero Rubin at the Battle of Las Guasimas in Cuba. The 1st US Volunteer Cavalry was the official name of, for ten points, what Spanish-American War-era cavalry unit containing Teddy Roosevelt?",
        "answer": [
          "Rough Riders",
          "1st US Volunteer Cavalry before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This colonel was the first commander of the Rough Riders and the man referenced in the “Weary Walkers” nickname.",
        "answer": "Leonard Wood"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "John Marshall",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State he represented in Congress; its other Congressmen included James Madison.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position he held under John Adams, for whom he negotiated an end to the Quasi War.",
          "answer": "Secretary of State"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who supposedly ranted “Marshall has made his decision, now let him enforce it!” after Worcester v Georgia.",
          "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legal principle established by Marshall’s decision in Marbury v Madison, allowing the Court to deem laws unconstitutional.",
          "answer": "judicial review"
        },
        {
          "question": "Institution deemed constitutional by Marshall in McCulloch v. Maryland.",
          "answer": [
            "a national bank",
            "Second Bank of the United States"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "New Hampshire college whose trustees sued the state for breach of contract; Daniel Webster’s moving speech persuaded Marshall.",
          "answer": [
            "Dartmouth College",
            "Trustees of Dartmouth College v. Woodward"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1810 case relating to the Yazoo land scandal, the first time a state law was ruled unconstitutional.",
          "answer": "Fletcher v. Peck"
        },
        {
          "question": "1833 case that ruled the Bill of Rights did not apply to the states, only the federal government.",
          "answer": "Barron v. Baltimore"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "1940 Fall of France",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Axis power that occupied a small section of southeast France after Germany conquered France.",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who evacuated to London during the Fall and later led Free France.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where over 300,000 people were evacuated across the English Channel at the end of May 1940.",
          "answer": "Dunkirk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Forest on the Belgian-French border that the German blitzkrieg stormed through.",
          "answer": "Ardennes Forest"
        },
        {
          "question": "Line of French forts and bunkers that the Germans avoided by invading through that forest.",
          "answer": "Maginot Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "armistice.",
          "answer": "Compiegne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Algerian city where the British attacked the French navy in July 1940 to prevent the Nazis from gaining the ships.",
          "answer": "Mers-el-Kebir"
        },
        {
          "question": "French port city where the Free French scuttled its own fleet in 1942 foiling Operation Anton.",
          "answer": "Toulon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Tokugawa Shogunate",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of the shogunate; you can give either its former or modern name.",
          "answer": "Edo or Tokyo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Feudal lords during the shogunate who employed samurai and obeyed the shogun.",
          "answer": "daimyo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Policy of isolationism held by the shogunate, which ended when Matthew Perry’s black ships arrived.",
          "answer": "sakoku"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group that was suppressed after the failed Shimabara Rebellion.",
          "answer": "Christians or Catholics"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor who took power in 1867 in the restoration that ended the Tokugawa Shogunate.",
          "answer": [
            "Emperor Meiji",
            "Meiji Restoration"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Civil war that began in 1868, after which Tokugawa loyalists formed the Ezo Republic.",
          "answer": "Boshin War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive battle in 1600 where Tokugawa’s forces defeated the Western Army, which was loyal to the Toyotomi clan.",
          "answer": "Battle of Sekigahara"
        },
        {
          "question": "Losing field commander in that battle who was captured and beheaded, signalling the decline of Toyotomi power.",
          "answer": "Ishida Mitsunari"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Richard Gott resigned from an editorial post for this publication after being accused of secretly negotiating with the KGB. Sarah Tisdall leaked information about the positioning of cruise missiles to this publication, which controversially defended the Widgery Tribunal in the aftermath of (20 pts)",
        "Bloody Sunday. David Cameron’s role in the Panama Papers was investigated by this newspaper, which broke the news of NSA surveillance programs leaked by (10 pts)",
        "Edward Snowden in 2013. The Observer is the sister newspaper to, for ten points, what British daily newspaper that was founded in Manchester and revealed the 2011 News phone hacking scandal?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Manchester Guardian"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the early 20th century, this state contracted some of its prison population to its northern neighbor until Commissioner of Charities and Corrections Kate Barnard investigated. A racist governor of this state, William Murray, boasted to farmers so much he earned the nickname “Alfalfa Bill.” A (20 pts)",
        "riot in this state began after Sarah Page was allegedly attacked by Dick Rowland in an elevator and resulted in a white mob setting fire to (10 pts)",
        "“Black Wall Street.” In 1889, the Indian Appropriations Act led to a land rush in, for ten points, what state where Greenwood race riot took place in Tulsa, decades after the “Boomers” and “Sooners” rushed in?"
      ],
      "answer": "Oklahoma"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. Fighting between these two countries nearly ended with the failed Zheleznovodsk [zhe-lezz-no-vodsk] Communique. The Black January pogrom broke out during fighting between these two countries. One of these two countries launched the large-scale (20 pts)",
        "Goranboy offensive against the other. The Lachin Corridor was awarded special status after the Bishkek Protocol ended fighting between these two countries. (10 pts)",
        "Stepanakert is the capital of a region contested by, for ten points, what two rival countries that fight over Nagorno-Karabakh and are governed from Baku and Yerevan?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Armenia and Azerbaijan",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire was victorious at the Battle of Avarayr against the Armenians, but granted them freedom of religion anyway. During a lengthy peace known as the Intermediate Era, this empire’s Yazdegerd I ended its persecution of Christians. A ruler of this empire allegedly flayed and (20 pts)",
        "dyed the skin of his rival vermillion after winning the Battle of Edessa against Valerian. This empire was founded after (10 pts)",
        "Artabanus V was defeated by Ardashir. Shapur the Great ruled, for ten points, what Persia-based empire that succeeded the Parthians?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sassanid Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After breaking off from this man’s party, Albert Kalonji created a federalist-leaning faction. During his country’s independence day celebrations, this leader called a former colonial power a “friendly country with whom we deal as equal to equal;” that 1961 speech was in the presence of King (20 pts)",
        "Badouin. A copper-rich region broke away from this man’s country under Moishe Tshombe and was known as (10 pts)",
        "Katanga. Four years after his death, this man’s country was ruled by Mobutu Sese Seko. For ten points, name this first prime minister of the Democratic Republic of the Congo."
      ],
      "answer": "Patrice Lumumba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Gill Bennett’s study of this document accuses Desmond Morton of having been its actual source. The namesake of this document claimed that it was “from the first to the last word, a forgery.” A unionist named (20 pts)",
        "Arthur McManus supposedly signed this document, which called to “develop the propaganda of ideas of Leninism.” The Daily Mail (10 pts)",
        "released this letter 4 days before Ramsay MacDonald lost the 1924 general election. For ten points, name this letter allegedly written to the Communist Party of Great Britain."
      ],
      "answer": "Zinoviev Letter"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A national museum in this country is housed in the Herat Citadel, on the site of a fort built by Alexander the Great. Elizabeth Thompson’s painting Remnants of an Army depicts William Brydon’s lonely horseride in this country, where William (20 pts)",
        "Elphinstone’s forces were slaughtered. During negotiations of the Treaty of Gandamak, John Burke photographed this country’s ruler, (10 pts)",
        "Mohammad Yaqud Khan, near the end of a 19th century war between Britain and this country. For ten points, name this country where Buddha statues in Bamiyan Valley were blown up by the Taliban in 2001."
      ],
      "answer": "Afghanistan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A vice-presidential candidate in this election year had taken over Walter Colquitt’s vacated Senate seat and would go on to become Governor of Georgia. In this election year, William Yancey, a member of the Fire-Eaters, helped (20 pts)",
        "split one party into geographic factions. The Lecompton Constitution was discussed during this election, whose winning ticket included (10 pts)",
        "Hannibal Hamlin. John Breckenridge and Stephen Douglas lost, for ten points, what Presidential election that helped trigger the siege of Fort Sumter after Abraham Lincoln won?"
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1860"
    }
  ]
}